OK, let's get started.
It seems like a usual Friday early in the semester.
We have some people still here.
That's good.
Not enjoying the nice weather outside.
You could make it a long weekend.
OK, those will come today.
We're going to continue where we stopped yesterday.
We were designing sequential logic and we figured out how to design memory structures.
What I'm going to do today is finish until the end of finite state machines.
Then we'll talk about labs and Fpgas.
And Otto work over here is ready to take over and discuss labs.
So if you have any tough questions on labs, he is the person to ask.
And Mayank, I don't know where he is, but Otto work is going to deliver the lecture.
Sounds good.
OK, OK, so let's dive in.
You know, there's an extra credit assignment some people ask questions about, like this 1%.
If you want to count the 1%, basically if you get 100 in this course and if you do the extra credit,
you'll get 101.
Sounds good, right?
If you get a 60 in this course and if you do the extra credit then you get the full grade, you'll
get a 61.
That's what 1% means.
OK, so today we're going to finish sequential logic, we'll do introduction to labs and very
unlikely, meaning we're not going to start hardware description language and very log, but that's
going to be next week.
And next week I hope to cover hardware description languages, very log and timing and verification.
So far we have not talked about timing.
It's going to be very important.
We'll, we'll still stay functional today, but we'll delve a little bit into timing when we talk
about finite state machines.
And timing is of course very important.
How long does it take for a circuit to evaluate?
And that's going to be very important for designing high performance as well as low power circuits.
Makes sense hopefully, right.
OK, so these are readings.
I'm going to skip that.
Now let's complete sequential logic design.
This is what we covered yesterday in sequential logic.
Basically, we figured out how to store information using combination logic elements.
We start with the cross coupled inverter.
And one of you said that this is useless kind of I'm, I'm revising what you said, of course, right,
because you cannot set that circuit.
And then we figured out how to set it using the Rs latch.
And then I said that this is bad because it breaks principle and it's also bad for practice because
you could get into situations where it becomes meta stable, where it oscillates in terms of the
value.
So we for we designed something that forbids a particular input combination where where RSRNS are
set and reset are both 0.
For that, we had the gated D latch, right?
Actually, we're not done with the flip flop, so I shouldn't have made that green.
So we also covered memory, how to design memories.
I'm going to show you a picture of that.
We also covered registers.
Today.
We're going to do the DS flip flop that shouldn't be over there.
Actually, basically today we're going to design sequential logic circuits.
We're going to introduce some new concepts like state clock, asynchronous synchronous design, and
also we will figure out that whatever we developed previously will not work for our purposes.
Then we're going to add more hardware to make that storage element more complex and you'll see that
it's not going to be nice, but it's going to work for our purposes.
Does that sound good?
So that so far we've acted a lot of hardware.
Actually, we started with a cross coupled inverter that's only four transistors and with the gated D
latch we got, we went up to 20 transistors or so.
Then we're going to double that soon and you'll see why.
OK, so this is the gated D latch.
If you remember, it's essentially 2 cross coupled inverters gated by two NAND gate.
Well emerged as I say, NAND gate, 2 cross coupled NAND gates gated by two other NAND gates to make
sure that you, you don't set the SNR to 0 at the same time.
OK, And this was the memory array.
So hopefully people remember this is just jog your memory and memory array in this particular case
was constructed with gated D latches.
And remember that we looked at how to decode the address so that we can read from a single row.
That's called a row of memory.
Essentially, you can read 3 bits at a time based on the address you're reading from.
And the there are four locations because you have two address bits.
So you can read from address 000110 and 11.
And you can also write to either of these addresses.
So these are the bits that you can write.
These are the inputs to the memory array.
So inputs are the.
The inputs, the address inputs and the right enabled inputs and the outputs are essentially the
whatever you read data inputs that are output makes sense, hopefully, right?
OK, I'll let you study it.
It will make sense.
And the book if you, if you actually need more information to study these, the lectures should be
enough for all of these.
But if you need more information, the books have additional explanations on these memory arrays.
Any questions in terms of memory?
OK.
And then we started talking about sequential logic circuits and this was the last slide that I left
you with because we did, we ran out of time essentially.
Now we have circuits that can store information, right?
We have different elements and gated D latch is our basic element that we're going to build on
because it has some nice properties that neither the cross coupled inverter nor the Rs latch have.
So what do we do with this?
So we want to build circuit elements that remember past inputs and do something useful, right?
For this, we need some other concepts in addition to what we've done so far.
And we're going to introduce the concept of state.
So I gave you this example yesterday and many of you said that you've used this one.
It's a combination of lock.
It doesn't remember what you've done in the past.
You basically set these values to something, the lock either opens or doesn't open, and next time
you set these values to something else and again it opens or doesn't open and it doesn't remember
what you've done previously, right?
So if you set it TO0000 first time, fine.
If you set it to 0001 next time, fine.
It doesn't remember any of this, right?
It opens when the values are set to a particular value, meaning the inputs.
It's only depend on the current input, right?
It doesn't remember what you've done in the past because it doesn't have any storage capability.
Whereas this one which fewer of you used, I think.
Is that still true or did did people start using it since yesterday?
Who knows, maybe maybe you want to try this is more secure, although for from a security
perspective, I think there's always an attacker who would attack either of them.
Yes.
Oh, OK.
You mean the combinational one?
Yeah, or the sequential one, I guess.
Yeah, I would say, OK.
When you when you turn open your phone, is it combinational?
Sequential.
I would say it's combinational because the first time, let's say you input the wrong code, it
doesn't.
The next time you input the right code, it will open, right?
It doesn't remember what has been done in the past.
It's sequential only in the sense that if you try too many times, it locks itself, right?
So it remembers how many times maybe you tried.
So in that sense, it's sequential.
But the opening action is, at a given point, purely combinational.
So that's a mix, I would say.
But this one is sequential because it opens depending on past inputs, right?
And let's take an example.
So this is the concept of state.
Basically, in order for this lock to work, it has to keep track of the past events or remember the
past events.
For example, you set the passcode in some way.
Let's say the passcode is you turn, you turn the dial to right to the to 13, to #13 and then you
turn it left to 22, and then you turn it right to three.
And only if you actually follow the sequence correctly, the lock is supposed to open, right?
That's your password basically.
OK, now initially the lock is not open, it's locked.
So there basically this, this lock has multiple states.
You can think of it that way.
Initially there's nothing that has been done.
It's locked and there's no input that's provided by the user.
So it's in a state, let's call a state A.
The lock is not open and there's no relevant operations have been performed by the user, no input,
basically.
That's a particular state.
Now there could be another state where this lock is locked but the user has input R13, right?
Makes sense, right?
It needs to remember that fact that the user has done R13 and only R13, OK?
And then there could be another state where the user has done R13 and then L 22, but the lock is
still locked, right?
And then there's another state that's called D again, what's called D Let's say the user has done
R13L22R3 in that sequence and the route lock recognizes that this is actually it needs to unlock.
So the output of the lock is unlocked.
Hopefully that makes sense, right, If that sequence of our patients have?
Have happened in this state, the lock should be unlocked.
OK, so basically I've given you multiple states of this lock and this is actually covers all of the
states with the minimal number of states.
Of course you can add more states, but it'll be redundant.
Essentially what what does the state of a system mean?
The state of a system is really the snapshot of all relevant elements of the system at the moment of
the snapshot, right?
All the relevant elements relevant to the operation of the system, right?
In this case, the what is relevant to the operation of the system inputs, what has been happened,
inputs and and also essentially what the state also could determine the output, right?
That's what you will see later on.
So for example, to open the lock states A to D must be completed in order, right?
So you need to go from A to B to C to D If you actually do something else, let's say let's say in
your state A, no, relevant operations haven't performed and the user does left 13.
They they make a mistake, instead of going to right 13, they do left 13.
Which state should lock go into?
Not a trick question, but maybe a trick question.
Yes, the starting state, essentially nothing important has happened.
Exactly.
Yeah.
Basically just stay at state A because the user did something that didn't really take the lock to a
position where it should be unlocked at some point, right?
Basically, it did some, it did something, they did something wrong, right?
Of course, you could design a lock that that actually goes to some other state potentially, right,
to punish the user, like like not take the next input, right?
That's possible.
But this lock doesn't behave that way.
OK, so basically, yeah, that's what it is.
It's if if anything else happens, for example, you do left five at any point in time, you return to
state A.
Actually at any point in time, if the except for state D, if the user inputs something that's out of
the sequence, the lock should return to state A, right.
OK, hopefully that's clear, right.
People know how to operate this lock and if you haven't operated it, you can try it and see what
happens.
So given this, so there's, this is a very powerful notion.
At a given point, you're in a state and you can actually describe what happens to the state based on
the inputs that you provide to this.
Let's call it a machine, right?
It's a machine.
It's a finite state machine actually, if you think about it.
But this state machine or state diagram completely describes the operation of the sequential lock,
right?
This is state A, the output, let's call it output.
It's in a locked state and if the user inputs anything other than R13, you stay in state A.
If the user inputs R13, the lock goes to state B, and at that point you're in a different state.
Now the lock observes what is the input.
If the user inputs anything other than left 22, you go back to state A.
If the user inputs L 22, meaning turns the the IL to left to 22, the lock goes to another state C,
which is essentially remembering the fact that the user has correctly inputted the sequence of
R13LL22.
Makes sense, right?
And in state C, if the user inputs anything other than R3, you go back to state A because it's wrong
essentially.
And otherwise, if the user inputs R3, the lock transitions into an open state.
And yeah, yeah, open state.
And if you think about it, yeah, this open state actually is an interesting state because the lock
is opened.
It's as if nothing has been done so far, right?
You open the lock, somebody needs to close the lock, right?
So you can actually stay in the state as kind of an A state.
If you think about it, if R13 comes again, you can directly go into the B state.
Hopefully that makes sense, Right.
Somebody needed to change the lock.
Of course, that's that.
That part is not shown over here in the state diagram.
Somebody needs to lock things again.
You could have changed the state diagram to take that into account also.
But your your book doesn't do that, so we'll do it that way.
So there could be multiple state diagrams that could actually describe the operation of this lock.
This is one of the state diagrams.
Does that make sense?
You could come up with a different state diagram.
Yes.
Well, what is special about R13 is because R13 is the correct sequence, right.
So somebody needs to close the lock and then do the R13 from the open state.
Yeah.
OK, it requires some thinking.
There's an assumption that's made over here, which is somebody close the lock before you.
They inputed R13.
OK, yeah, books are not always fully comprehensible, so you need to think.
I found some other bug today when I was looking at some of the explanations in one of the books, but
that's OK.
OK.
OK, so this is actually a state diagram and we'll see more of these.
There's a particular thing about this part, this thing, but I which I would like to introduce this
is an asynchronous system.
I want to introduce this asynchronous versus synchronous systems.
Yes, I had a question about the state.
Yes, C state to B state.
How would you go there?
When you input R13, you need to open like there needs to be some action where the things thing gets
the lock opens, right?
If you're in C state.
Oh OK.
If you're in C state, when you input R, if you input R13, you did the wrong thing.
The lock should not open and it should be as if nothing happened so far, right?
No, because you you you've broken the sequence.
You should do R13L22R3.
So it's only a lock from D state?
Exactly.
Yes.
OK, I'll let you think about it.
OK, so this is an asynchronous machine.
This sequential lock we saw is actually an asynchronous machine because state transitions take place
immediately in response to input, right?
Meaning the user provides some input, the machine transitions, the lock transitions to some other
state.
This is important.
There's an immediate reaction, right?
There is no delay, or there's nothing else that's happening that waits for something to synchronise.
Now, yeah, there is essentially nothing that synchronises when each state transition must occur.
Now, for reasons we're not really going to go into a whole lot in this course, this is not an easy
design.
If you want to design a full computer fully asynchronously, it's very hard to make sure different
parts of a computer work.
Correctly.
At the same time, there's a lot of parallelism that happens in a computer and you will see some of
that in your labs.
So most modern computers as a result are synchronous machines.
What does this mean?
This means that state transitions happen at fixed units of time.
There's something, there's potentially a delayed response to input and there it's synchronised to an
external signal, meaning you divide time into chunks and when you input something, the response
comes a bit later or you take in, take, take that input into account a bit later.
So basically you're going to control the system by a clock.
And when the clock is, let's say positive or negative, then we can do the state transition.
We're going to assume positive in the rest of this lecture, but it could be negative also.
So basically, we're going to change the state only at particular times in a point as opposed to when
the input comes.
Hopefully that makes sense right now.
This will ease the design significantly because we're going to make sure that we can do everything
within a clock cycle.
And I'm going to introduce the notion of clock.
That's why notion of clock is really important.
But these are, in the end, two different design paradigms with different trade-offs.
I will talk about the trade-offs a little bit later, but to understand the notion of clock, let's
take a look at another example of state.
This is how many people drive here, how many people don't drive?
OK, that's good.
I guess.
How many people have seen a traffic light?
OK, How many people have not?
OK, I guess maybe one person.
OK.
So basically if you look at a Swiss traffic light, I say Swiss traffic light because different
traffic lights in different parts of the world have different ways of changing.
So it essentially has four states.
The traffic lights in can be in the green state, yellow state, red state, and then red and yellow
state.
Is it still correct?
I don't drive so I don't remember.
I don't pay attention to these either, OK?
Anyway, when I'm not driving, I shouldn't pay attention to this, right?
I should pay attention to some other light maybe when I'm crossing, OK.
Basically, the sequence of these states are always as follows.
We're going to assume that we're going to stay an equal amount of time in each state.
You can change that relatively easily.
So you're in state A.
After some time you transition to state B.
There is no input.
We're going to change that.
Also at the end of this lecture, we're going to design A slightly smart but somewhat stupid traffic
light.
But this traffic light has no smartness.
It doesn't take in take into account any input.
The only input is a notion of time, meaning clock, right?
So you go from state A to state B after, I don't know, let's say 5 seconds, you go from state B to.
It goes from state B to state C after another 5 seconds.
It goes from state C to state D after another 5 seconds.
OK, maybe it's not the best flight you want, but that's how it is.
And then eventually you return from state D to state A after another 5 seconds.
So every state you stay 5 seconds in.
So how do you accomplish something like this?
How do you enable something like this?
And that's where the clock comes in.
And that's actually basically this is the basics of synchrony, right?
We're going to ignore any other input other than clock.
And we want to synchronise the transitions of the state to when the clock changes.
OK, When should the light change from one state to another?
We're going to introduce this notion of clock, which will dictate when to change the state.
We're going to generate a signal, and you can generate the signal.
In modern machines, there are clock signal generators that will oscillate.
Or I shouldn't say oscillate.
Maybe alternate between state zero and one, logic zero and logic one.
It'll start with a rising edge.
It'll stay at high and it'll fall.
This is the falling edge of the clock.
It'll stay at 0, it'll rise.
Basically, it'll do this forever while the computer is powered on.
Sounds good, right?
It's a digital signal.
It's generated by an analogue signal generator, like a crystal oscillator, for example.
But it's a digital signal in the end, and we're going to treat as a digital signal.
So this is from your book, one of the books.
This is basically 1 clock cycle.
We're going to call the distance between 1 rising edge to another rising edge 1 clock cycle, OK.
And we can set the clock cycle for this example to 5 seconds, right?
Does that make sense?
Yeah.
OK.
So this notion will be important for designing circuits.
OK, So essentially at the start of this clock cycle, meaning at the rising edge, the system state
changes.
During the clock cycle, the state stays constant.
And in this traffic light example, we're assuming the traffic light stays in each state any an equal
amount of time.
Now this is a very simple circuit in the sense that there's nothing happening in the clock cycle
other than we're outputting a signal, right?
But we will see circuits soon, very soon where you change the state and then you need to do some
computation and you go to a different state based on what happens in that computation and you will
do some other computation in the next state.
OK, so for you to really do something interesting with that type of circuitry, you need to set the
clock cycle long enough such that you do that that computation finishes.
Does that make sense?
It'll become more and more clear as we go through this, but I would like to introduce this right
now, this machine doesn't do any computation during the clock cycle other than outputting a
particular colour of light, right?
But at the beginning of clock cycle, it changes the state.
If you want to design A more complicated machine, maybe you do some computation, right?
For example, let me give you an example.
We're not going to design this yet.
We're going to design A more stupid version of it.
For example, in state A, you count how many you have some circuitry that counts how many cars are
going from different directions, right?
That's some sort of computation.
And if the number of cars is greater than some threshold, maybe you stay in state A, right?
That's some computation.
Does that make sense?
So now you have a more intelligent light, potentially if the number of cars is greater than 5 in
this particular light, and then you maybe consider some other directions also, then you stay in the
state.
You should have enough time to do that computation right during that clock cycle.
If you don't have enough time to do that computation, you will not be able to decide that you'll
stay in this state.
OK, so we'll get to this.
So this is the notion of finite state machines that will come up.
Any questions?
OK, so clock is really a general mechanism that triggers transition from one state to another in a
synchronous sequential circuit.
I'm going to assume synchronous sequential circuit soon, because clock really is the synchroniser,
right?
It really synchronises the state changes across many sequential circuit elements.
We will see how to design A microprocessor.
A microprocessor will not have only one component, it will have thousands of components.
Well, we're not going to do thousands in this course, but it will really have thousands of
components and there will be different circuits doing different things.
They're all sequential circuits.
How do you ensure that they're all synchronised?
Clock is essentially distributed everywhere on a chip and we will see that.
So combinational logic evaluates for the length of the clock cycle, which is what I mentioned.
Basically you, you change to a different state and you look at inputs and you have some
combinational logic that evaluates, meaning you do some computation using combinational logic and
the clock cycle should be chosen to accommodate that combinational, accommodate the longest
combinational delay in that combinational logic, meaning that computation should be finished before
the rising edge of the clock comes, arrives.
OK.
Otherwise you're, you don't, you don't give enough time for the computation.
Make sense?
This will become more and more clear as we study finite state machines.
And then once we go into timing, you will see that you will really need to take into account how
long it takes for the combination of logic to evaluate and that will really determine our clock
cycle.
OK, more on this one.
We discussed timing.
Right now you should know that there's state, there's clock state changes happen at the rising edge
of the clock.
I'm going to assume that and you need to give enough time for the combinational logic to compute
whatever it's computing before the rising edge of the clock arrives.
OK, so this is synchronous versus asynchronous.
Let's get back to this Clock enables us to synchronise these different state elements.
Now, synchronous control is usually easier to get correct, especially when the system consists of
many components and many states.
I said can be easier, but actually it's always easier.
Asynchronous design is actually usually very difficult, especially when you have lots of inputs,
lots of things that are changing.
But it could be more efficient because there is no clock overheads.
And we will see that also in the timing lecture clock introduced an overhead like state doesn't
change until the clock changes, right?
Yeah, yeah, I mean, certainly asynchronous is needed when you're dealing with external inputs,
right?
You need to have some asynchronous logic that takes the external input and synchronizes later with
the remaining synchronized synchronous logic.
So every computer has.
Yeah, certainly there's some asynchronous logic that's needed, but there aren't.
Yeah, unfortunately not.
There's a lot of research in that area.
Relatively few people are doing research in that area right now.
But it's very difficult to enable completely asynchronous CPU.
That's why you see CPUs all advertised with clock frequencies, right?
OK, OK.
So we will assume synchronous systems in most of this course of scratch that, most, maybe all of
this course.
OK, so these are some examples of synchronous sequential circuit except for the top one.
This is actually a nice figure from your book.
If you're interested, you can take a look at it.
This is a combinational logic circuit, right?
CL is combinational logic, meaning there is no state element.
Now this is combinational logic.
And then there is a state element and we're going to introduce a clock going into the state element.
Basically state elements will be a.
You can, you can write to the state element only at the rising edge of the clock.
And we will see why this will be necessary soon.
OK, so this is a sequential logic type.
So you have some inputs, you evaluate the inputs, and then eventually you store the inputs when the
clock is at the rising edge.
And then something happens afterwards.
This is not a very completely useful circuit, as you will see, because it does only one evaluation,
right?
Or maybe it keeps evaluating something and.
Then outputting something that's a very simple circuit, I shouldn't say it's not very useful.
It's, well, it's, it's correct that it's not very useful.
Many, many systems don't behave this way, but the other two are quite useful.
This is a finite state machine, as we will see, one sort of finite state machine.
Basically, you have some combination logic.
There are some inputs, there's some state, and the previous state, like whatever you stored over
here is also input to the combination logic.
So you do some computation on inputs coming from outside, plus whatever you remember, and then you
output and then you store that in the next cycle.
And you can keep doing this basically based on the new inputs coming.
This is kind of our lock, except it's synchronous, right?
And then outputs are essentially based on some other combinational logic.
We will see this very soon.
This is a finite state machine and later in the course, so this is useful.
You can do many things with it.
You can implement synchronous locks for example.
Now later in this course we will actually combine these together and in the timing of lecture
actually we will talk about this also.
This is you can see that this is you get some inputs, you put them in a state register as we will
define.
And then at the rising edge of the clock, everything happens at the rise.
The, the, the, the registers, the memories over here are updated at the rising edge of the clock.
And then there's some combination logic that evaluates and you have a full clock cycle during which
it evaluates at the end of the clock cycle, which means at the beginning of the next clock cycle at
the rising edge of the clock.
The results of this are placed into this register such that in the next cycle, whatever combination
logic comes after this can operate on those results, and then it can operate and then it'll latch
the results.
This is a form of logic called pipelining.
What we're doing is really pipelining computation.
Inputs are coming in from the left, and the combination logic is evaluating.
Every cycle you're latching new results, and those new results will be the input to the next stage
in the pipeline.
OK.
All modern processors are built this way.
Basically, I wanted to do this notion at this time because you may ask the question, why are we
dealing with this?
This is exactly what we, what we will build.
And this is exactly how we can parallelise computation because while the stage is doing something,
the stage will be doing something else.
OK, hopefully that makes sense.
And this is how we can synchronise an entire machine, basically.
You can imagine thousands of these operating concurrently, but they're doing different things at
different parts, Yes.
Doesn't change too fast for the memory block to versus store the result.
Yeah.
So basically the the key is to make sure that the combination of logic delay is shorter than your
clock cycle, right?
Yeah, but it does need to be longer than the store cycle, the store time for the memory block,
right?
Which memory block?
We're going to talk about that in the timing.
Don't, don't get ahead of yourself right now.
Yeah, well, we're going to talk about all of those.
The key to remember right now is but yes, exactly.
There are some other delays associated with it, but combinational logic, whatever you're doing in
this combination logic should be shorter than the clock cycle time.
OK, OK, mini clock cycle time.
Remember what that is the the time between the first rising edge of the clock and the second rising
edge next rising edge.
So the clock rises, stays, goes down and then rise again.
That's the clock cycle time, OK.
That's how we will determine the clock cycle.
Also in the timing lecture, yes, how long a certain operation takes.
We'll talk about that in the timing lecture.
So there's an operation.
OK, maybe I'll quickly answer that because you know exactly what you've implemented.
A NAND gate for example, right?
You know, the delay of a NAND gate, somebody provides that and you can also simulate it.
So it can basically combine all of those, as we will do in the timing lecture, and you will figure
out how long a sequence of gates will take.
But yeah, these are good questions, but they are related to the timing lecture.
OK, so let's talk about finite state machines a little bit.
So now I'm kind of built up to finite state machines.
This is a finite state machine, and we're going to look at that structure actually a lot.
So what is a finite state machine?
It's really a discrete time model of a stateful system.
You divide you divide time into a discrete intervals and you describe a stateful system based on
what happens at different time intervals.
Each state really represents a snapshot of the system at a given time, and NFSM or Finite State
Machine pictorially shows the set of all possible states that a system can be in and how the system
transitions from one state to another.
Now it can model a traffic light, an elevator, fan speed, many, many things.
A microprocessor.
Every microprocessor is a finite state machine.
It's a big finite state machine.
It's a complicated finite state machine with potentially millions, maybe even billions of states
depending on what you have, what you consider a system.
But it is a finite state machine.
It enables us to pictorially think of a stateful system using simple diagrams.
Actually, a microprocessor consists of many finite state machines that interact with each other, and
in the end that's also a finite state machine.
OK, so a finite state machine consists of five elements, a finite number of states.
It's not a infinite.
Basically, we've already discussed what a status snapshot of all relevant elements of the system at
the time of the snapshot.
A finite number of external inputs, A finite number of external outputs.
An explicit specification of how you transition from one state to another and an explicit
specification of what determines each external output value, how that is computed essentially or
not exactly how it's computed, but what output value you get in a given state and based on the
inputs.
So we're going to build finite state machines and it's it'll consist of three things basically.
One is next state logic, the other is state register, the other is Optip logic.
Let's take a look at each of these.
So next state state register is essentially what is your, what is the state you're in at this point
in time?
OK, that determines your state.
There is next state logic which takes inputs and the current state and that determines what should
your next state be based on the current inputs and the current state and output logic determines
what is, what are your outputs based on the current state and sometimes based on the inputs as
well.
Yes.
Is that a cost of time to change from a state to another?
And there's always a cost of time, there's always latency to change from one state to another.
It'll take time basically to decide.
That's the combination of logic basically.
OK, we'll talk more about that in the timing again.
So this is the state register.
And at the beginning of the clock cycle, this is again, we're, we're getting back to this.
At the beginning of the clock cycle, next state is lashed into the state register so that you
essentially at the beginning of the clock cycle, you transition to the next state and then you are
in that state until the end of the clock cycle.
We're going to get back to that again.
So we have essentially sequential circuits, which is state register as a sequential circuit.
It takes as input the next state and its output as the current state, OK.
And you S becomes S prime only when the clock is rising.
So it stores the current state and provides the next state at the clock edge.
Makes sense, right?
Combinational circuits also exist.
There's a next state logic that's combinational.
It determines what the next state will be, and the output logic generates the outputs.
OK, hopefully it's clear so far.
Now we'll have a problem with the sequential part of this.
How do we implement the state register?
Basically, based on what I said and based on what I motivated, you need 2 properties here.
You need to change the value in the register or store data at the beginning of every clock cycle,
right?
Clock transition determines when the input is acquired at the rising edge.
That's called the rising edge of the clock.
You can see that clock is rising over here, right?
And the data in that register must be available during the entire clock cycle, meaning it shouldn't
change even though inputs may be changing, right?
Because we want to do something with that state value inside it so that we do some useful
computation during that entire clock cycle, right?
So basically, while the clock is changing, this is the desired output.
There could be an input into the register.
This is the maybe when, when I say register input, this is the register that I'm talking about.
It's a state register.
I'm I'm plotting essentially S prime and S over here.
Register input is S prime, register output is S So you can see that this is the desired behaviour we
want.
Input may change as prime may change over here, but because it didn't change in the rising edge, I
don't care about this change.
My output or S should not change because what might be happening is some some sort of calculation is
happening in the combination logic and you will see that circuit will be settling.
What I really care about is at the end of the clock cycle or at the beginning of the next clock
cycle.
So this is our desired behavior.
Hopefully everyone everyone's with me.
OK, what should happen is as you can see over here, register inputs which is S prime.
The input to the state register changed over here.
It was 0 here and the output was zero.
That zero got reflected.
Oh sorry, that one.
The change to one got reflected at the rising clock edge because at the rising clock edge that one
was stable.
OK.
That means circuit has evaluated until that clock cycle and it produced a result and I can trust it
at the rising clock edge assuming I designed my circuit based on the timing properties as we will
discuss in the next next Friday.
It shouldn't change over here because this thing that happened did not happen at the rising clock
edge.
And then the register output became 0 from what they went from 1 to 0 because the input become
became the input went from one to zero and it's it, it persisted until the rising clock edge.
OK.
We did not change the state here immediately.
It was more delayed and we definitely did not change the state based on this because it was
potentially what we will call a glitch later on in the timing lecture, right.
OK, yes, yeah.
Then you will latch it.
You will, you will put it into the state.
Now the question becomes is that the right thing to do?
That depends on whether you designed the combinational logic circuit correctly such that you did the
correct computation makes sense.
You will see more of this.
So it may be a correct thing, but based on our design, it's probably not a correct thing over here
because it in the end the combinational logic didn't evaluate that result at the rising clock edge,
right?
So the key is to design the combinational logic and the clock cycle such that your combinational
logic finishes its evaluation when the rising edge comes.
OK, so that could be correct behaviour, assuming you did everything correctly.
OK, so now we have a problem, right?
Unfortunately, we have not seen a storage element that provides us desired behaviour.
Everything we have seen is bad from this perspective.
And let's take a look at why the D latch is bad.
So this is our gated D latch.
Beautiful.
And we want the clock, right because we don't want the right enable anymore.
Right enable, we want to change the state on a clock edge.
So let's assume that we want to wire the right.
We want to wire the clock to the right enable signal.
So whenever the clock is high, the latch propagates D to Q.
This is based on what you remember right.
Whenever we set the right enable, Q becomes D, right?
Similarly, if you, if you actually, if you actually make wire clock to right enable, whenever the
clock is high, Q gets D In a sense the latch is transparent, right?
While the clock is high or while the right enable is high, Q will be D.
But that's not the behaviour we want it.
We want the we want Q to be equal to D only when the clock is rising, not when the clock is high.
Now let me show you this one.
So this is our clock, this is our input, the previous input S prime.
And this is what you would get if you actually wire that clock to the right naval signal of the D
latch.
So there are two problems here.
1 is this.
Whenever the clock is high, you'll get 0.
So you'll get you'll, you'll basically get the glitch inside your state register, which means that
your state changes during the clock cycle and your combinational logic that you designed for that
clock cycle is messed up.
And there's another problem over here.
When this state, this input gets reflected immediately in the output of the state register because
the clock is I over here.
In this particular case, you were lucky because this input changed when the clock was low, right?
So luckily you did the right thing.
But here you were unlucky.
OK, so this design doesn't satisfy our requirement, so we need something else and that's something
else will come at a cost.
OK, basically, how do we change the latch?
Latch has some desirable properties, but it's not behaving as we want.
What we want is really the D input to be observable at Q output only at the beginning of the next
clock cycle.
And we want Q to be available for the full clock cycle, right?
That's what we want.
So essentially we need storage.
Elements that allow us to read the current state throughout the entire current clock cycle and not
write the next state values into the storage elements until the beginning of the next clock cycle.
So that's why we introduced the flip flop.
I didn't name it that way.
It was named this way, but it's very, it's not a bad name, I guess.
So we're going to double our circuitry.
We have this D latch, the first one, and we're going to add another D latch, a second one, and the
first D latch will make sure that you don't propagate the change in D to Q when the clock is
anything other than the rising edge.
So basically this is how we're going to wire the clock to each.
This may not look intuitive initially, but it's going to behave the way we we want.
So the clock bar goes here and the clock goes here.
So this is the right enable signal, remember?
So when the clock is high, this will be right enabled.
When the clock is low, this will be right enabled.
OK, let's take a look at how this behaves.
When the clock is low, the first latch propagates D to the input of the second latch.
So Q doesn't get changed.
There's some value in Q Forget about it.
It doesn't get changed when the clock is low.
Because when the clock is low, what happens is this will be right enabled and this value over here,
which is the output of the first latch will be set to D OK, that's based on what we learnt.
Now, only when the clock is high, the second latch latches D meaning when the clock is high over
here, this right enable will be 1 and Q will get whatever was here right that achieved what we
wanted.
Basically meaning at the only at the rising edge of the clock, Q gets assigned D, right?
And it'll stay as D because we'll stay at the right, we'll stay at level one.
OK, so it's a beautiful design.
It just doubled our area cost more than doubled actually, because you have an inverter added.
Sounds good.
OK, so that's the D flip flop.
We normally essentially at the rising edge of the clock, Q gets assigned D at all other times, Q is
unchanged.
And that's what that's how we show the flip flop as you can also get Q bar clearly with any type of
latch, you may be able to use Q bar for some computation, right?
That's why you also supply Q bar.
Now we can use D flip flops to implement the state register.
So essentially we have two inputs, clock and D and then function is it samples D on the rising edge
of the clock.
We call all call this also positive edge.
And I think I've already said all of this.
It's it's it's all just previous value except for the rising edge of the clock.
This is because This is why it's called an edge triggered state element.
Basically you trigger, you change the state only when the clock edge happens.
Now the reason why latch did not work by itself is because it was a level triggered state element.
The state changed based on the level, not based on the edge.
OK, you may see these in digital design A lot.
OK, now we've gotten away from an hurdle.
Yes.
Not currently, yeah.
OK, so essentially deep flip flop based register is very similar to AD latch based register, except
it consists of D flip flops.
Each of them stores one bit and you can condense it.
This is a 4 bit D flip flop.
For example, base register, right?
This register stores 4 bits.
This is just notation and each line represents 4 wires.
So whenever you see this notation, you will see that each line represents 4 bits essentially.
And this is internally what it looks like.
This is a 4 bit D flip flop based register.
It's expensive as you can see.
OK, now let's build some finite state machines.
Next state is determined by the current state and the inputs.
There are actually two types of finite state machines that different output logic.
I don't like the naming of these unfortunately and I always confuse them.
I don't expect you to remember these things, but the the key distinction is whether the output
depends only on the current state or the output depends on the current state as well as the inputs.
So this is more finite state machine and this is merely finite state machine and in more output
depends only on the current state.
As you can see, output logic takes only current state and supplies some outputs, and merely output
logic takes the current state and the inputs and supplies outputs.
So this was our synchronous sequential circuits.
Now we're going to build a finite state.
Machine example.
So I think what I will do is I will finish this example and then we will take a break and then auto
work will continue.
Does that sound good?
OK, this example will go relatively quickly because we've built a lot of concepts over here and it's
a smart traffic light controller.
It's also from your book, basically there you can see that there are two avenues, Academic Ave.
and Bravada, that's called A&B Avenues.
And there are two traffic lights, TA that are essentially the same, then TB over here on both sides.
And well, yeah, there are two traffic sensors TA and TBTA is essentially true or high when there's
traffic, otherwise it's slow.
And TB is also when there's traffic on Ave.
ATB is high when there's traffic on Ave.
B, otherwise it's zero.
And there are two outputs.
Each light can be red, yellow and green.
I guess in this particular case we have only three states.
In some parts of the world you have only three states.
And the traffic light, I made that mistake once, said OK anyway, so state changes every 5 seconds.
It's kind of similar to what we have done earlier, except we're going to introduce something smart
or stupid depending on your perspective.
Except if there's if, if, if the light is green on Ave.
X, let's say, and there's traffic on Ave.
X, it will stay green, which means that this will be a, if you think about like fairness and
starvation, this is actually a very bad design.
11 Avenue may star forever, right?
OK, so essentially we're going to design the traffic light controller, which is a finite state
machine.
You have 3-4 inputs, clock, reset, TA and TB.
The reset is useful for resetting the state to the a known state at the very beginning of operation.
It will be there for every finite state machine.
I'm just introducing it right now, but it's something that you need to think about in the design.
And then there are two outputs, light A and light B.
And these are multiple bits because you have three states, right?
Three possible colours in light.
OK, now for the way you design this is you first need to build the transition diagram.
Let's do more.
FSM outputs are labeled in each state.
Outputs are a function of the state only.
States are circles.
Transitions are arcs.
There is a reset state, which is where you begin with, right?
We're going to assume that Avenue A will be green and Avenue B will be red.
OK.
That's state zero And we're going to transition to if there's traffic on Ave.
A at the clock cycle at the rising edge of the clock, we're going to stay in State 0 right at the
rising edge of the clock.
If there is no traffic in, in, in Avenue A, we're going to go to state one and state one will turn
the light on Avenue A to yellow and light on Ave.
B to red.
OK.
And that state 2 is easy transition.
It's it doesn't depend on the input because the light is yellow.
So you go to state 2 where light on Avenue A turns red, light on Ave.
B becomes green, green.
Now if there's traffic on B, you stay in state 2.
If there's no traffic on B, you go to state 3 where light on Avenue A is still red, but light on
Ave.
B becomes yellow.
And then you unconditionally transition at the rising edge of the next clock cycle or the clock
cycle to state 0.
Sounds good, right?
This is the design for the smart traffic light.
Now how do you actually design it?
I'll go through this relatively quickly.
Now, based on this, you have current state.
So first we want to actually get the state transition table, right?
This is current state on the left.
You have the current state and then you have the inputs.
And based on both, you determine the next state, right?
And we're going to, we can, we can easily provide a truth table for this current.
If the currency is at 0, regardless of what happens on Ave.
B, we'll go to state one if there's no light, no traffic on Avenue A Otherwise we go to state zero.
And you can see that you can construct all of this.
If the current is this one, regardless of the inputs, we go to state 2, right?
Because we transition 5 seconds later or whatever that clock cycle is.
Now you can actually encode the states in some way.
You have 4 States and you can encode them with log 2 to the north number of bits, 2 bits essentially
and change your truth table.
Now this is a full truth table right now and based on what we have seen in the past, you can do sum
of products form for each of the output variables which is S1 prime and S 0 prime.
These are the two bits that store the next state.
So I will let you do this because you know sum of products form, but essentially very quickly you
basically combine you, you look at this.
This is where S1 is 1, S one prime is 1, and S1 prime is essentially equal to.
S1 bar and S0 or S1S0 bar TB bar.
Good, I'm getting it right.
And then you can do the other one.
OK, so this is sum of products form and you do the same thing for S0 prime and then you reduce the
equation.
So now we know exactly how to compute each of the state bits for the next state S1, prime and S10
based on inputs and the current state inputs TATB and current state bits S1S0 output table you can
construct similarly.
This is essentially outputs are dependent only on the current state.
This is our current state S1S0.
These are the outputs LA and LB, light A and light B.
And what we're going to do is encode the colours.
Green is 00, yellow is 01, red is 10.
You need 2 bits, then called 3 colours and again do the same thing, sum of products forms and you
will get the values of each of the output bits LA1LA0L AL, B1LB0.
OK, and this is our schematic.
Now we can actually put whatever we construct into our schematic.
This is our state register S1 and S0 is our state 2 bits.
This is S1 prime S 0 prime that will be latched at the rising edge of the clock cycle.
And this is the next state logic that we constructed.
I put them as gates, but this is the Boolean equations and this is the output logic.
OK, so this is essentially our finite state machine.
We just constructed the full finite state machine based on what we've learnt so far, based on a
specification of how a smart traffic light operates.
Does that sound good?
OK.
So I'm not going to talk about this timing diagram.
We're going to get to timing later on.
How do you do the state encoding?
It's interesting, but maybe I'll talk about it a bit later.
But there are multiple ways of doing state encoding.
There are trade-offs associated with it.
I'll let you study these slides actually for that Moore versus Mealy machines.
We've already discussed this.
I will not go through this in detail again, but there's a nice example from your book on how to
construct.
I'll, I'll maybe you describe the problem so that you can work on it on your own or during the lab
sessions.
Essentially, there's a snail that crawls down on a paper tape with ones and zeros on it.
The snail smiles whenever the last four digits it has crawled over R1101.
And you design A state machine that does this.
It's kind of similar to the lock that we've discussed, right?
Yeah.
And this is the Moore FSM and Media FSM.
And there are trade-offs over here that I'm not going to talk about right now.
So we have constructed a state machine.
The best way of really learning about state machines is constructing more of them.
You're going to do a lot of these in your labs, and Attabark is going to talk about labs very soon,
but this is 1, let's say 1 slide description of how you construct it.
You determine all possible states.
You develop a state transition diagram.
For this.
You need inputs and outputs for each state, how to get from one state to another.
And then you need to have a reset state.
This is really important.
Where does your system start?
All microprocessors have a reset state.
When you power up, things get reset and then basically you need some things.
But we're not going to talk about that right now.
So what is to come?
Everything we will build will have finite state machines.
This is something you will see in later lectures.
There will be a finite state machine.
We will discuss that.
Everything will be dictated by the operation of a finite state machine in a microprocessor, and
we'll discuss how that finite state machine controls the operation of the system.
But I for for the purpose of the next lectures, remember this diagram over here, we're designing
sequential circuits, but these sequential circuits will operate in conjunction with other
sequential components in the system.
So you will not be alone.
It's not you're going to be a single register, single combinational logic, Forget about it.
It's going to be register combination logic, register combination logic, register combination logic,
register combination logic.
Everything we've discussed so far will be combined together.
How to do that, you'll have to wait a little bit.
OK, let's take a break right now.
How much time do you need at the back?
OK, great.
So we'll we'll take I'll give you 31 minutes.
So we'll take a 15 minute break.
We'll be back at 1529 and then I'll come back.
We'll talk about labs.
Testing can can they?
Can you hear me?
No.
Can the room hear me?
I think so, yeah.
OK, can you hear us?
All?
Good.
OK, let's get started.
So in the remaining time Atabach from, you know already, he is the head TA for the labs along with
Mayank in the back is going to introduce the labs.
And also he's going to delve into Fpgas a little bit.
We very briefly covered the look up tables in Fpgas, but he's going to tell you more about what
Fpgas are good for, what we use them for and how they are constructed at some level.
And you can ask him questions at the end if you have any questions about the labs.
OK, go ahead.
OK, thank you for the introduction.
And as Professor Mutla said, I personally want to convey what you can use Fpgas for beyond this
lecture, in this in this lecture, basically beyond this course.
So that will be my primary goal for this lecture.
And we'll start with some logistics.
We'll get logistics out of the way.
We covered them already in one of the previous lectures.
We will have the lab sessions in these rooms that you see here on the dates that we show here and at
these times of the day.
If you have any questions about these, you can send us emails at the link you see down below.
OK, maybe not in this slide.
OK, you can send us emails to the digital technique mailing list.
I'll show you in the next slide the e-mail address.
And in the labs you will work in groups of two.
You've already selected your partner.
Perhaps if you didn't select your partner, don't worry, we will match you up with someone else and
you will receive an FPGA board.
We will see what an FPGA board is later in this lecture and we want you to be there in the first
week of the labs, either you or your partner so that you can get your FPGA boards delivered to you
and you will collect them on the exam date.
So you will hold on to them.
Hopefully you won't break them, but sometimes you know, unfortunate things can happen.
So you can follow model for details about the logistics.
I'll talk a little bit about grading.
We want to help you successfully complete all the labs.
That's are basically that's, that's our that's what we want to make sure we provide for you.
There will be 10 labs.
You will get 30 points in total from the 10 labs each.
Each lab will provide three points to your overall course grade.
You will put all the lab manuals online.
You can find them at this link.
We'll have two components for grading.
So first we will evaluate the in the class based on what you do for the lab handouts we hand out to
you.
And basically the format for this will be you will work on lab handouts for a week with your partner
and two hours out of those out of that week will be in the lab in the rooms here where you will
have TAS to talk to and ask questions about if you're, if you're stuck.
And the following week after we release the lab handouts, the TAS will ask you about your work.
You will show them your work, you will explain what you did and we'll get the 70% out of the 100%
points that way.
And you will also have lab reports, which will comprise 30% of the lab points.
And we expect you to submit them two weeks after we release these.
There is a small penalty for late lab reports.
And you can also use your grades for labs from the past years if you've attended this course earlier
for questions.
Yes, this is the e-mail.
You can, this is the mailing list that you can send your emails to.
You can ask me questions if you see me around or Mayank, he's on the back over there.
We'll be happy to help you out with partner assignments also.
So OK, I'll touch on this for the first time, I think in the history of DDCA explicitly.
So we have a tentative AI policy.
We want you to do the labs on your own, work with your partner and use the resources that we provide
you in the labs to complete your work.
And you can ask questions to the teaching assistants now there, I think.
Before we go there, we will ask you to explain how you did the labs and what you did in the labs.
So it will be relatively easy for us to understand if you've used AI assistance or not.
And you should truly understand the labs because for the longer term, because there may be questions
from the lab material on the exam.
Now there are two other reasons why you, I think you don't need to use AI in this course in the in
the labs.
These are designed assuming you will do them on your own, so excessive AI assistance might yield a
different learning experience for you.
And each lab requires two or three hours of focused work really.
And you don't save much time by using AI if you ask me.
Assuming you're saving it right, you you might lose time also if if you're misled and I think AI
could help you in places where this will become more clear as you do the labs.
There will be some obscure design tool errors that your TAS will help you with.
But these are the things that you could use AI to help you sort of get out of the way.
OK.
Do you have any questions so far about logistics?
Yes, just on the grade, it is purely in Group, like if my partner and me, we always end in the same
thing, so we'll always get the same grade, right?
Yes, if you collaborate on the lab.
So the question is, do we get graded?
Do both partners get the same grade?
Yes, that's what we want to do and that's what happens usually.
Sometimes you will not be able to work with your partner effectively and then we will know.
Ideally, we ask you to tell us about these things.
Yes.
What if you're sick on a day Does did you get 0 points for that lab?
No, no.
Pretty lenient.
Given that you've did your work, you might not appear on a certain lab.
Your partner can present that for you.
That's that's OK as as long as it doesn't repeat a lot of times.
Right.
OK So what will you learn in OK Yeah.
Another religious.
Right.
So you will be in the labs for two hours where you can receive assistance from the T as.
And outside of those labs hours, depending on like how much it took you personally, you might need
to work a little bit more with your partner so that you can show your work the following week.
So we don't expect you to complete the labs during the lab session for all the labs.
But you can also do it.
I mean, it's most students do it.
Yeah.
So basically, we release the labs, you attend one session, and then the next session you're graded
for the lab.
So you have a whole week to work on the lab handouts.
Yeah.
Oh no, they're both created.
So the handout is different from the reports, the different content.
You do the handouts in the labs, you show your work in the following week and then you great, get
graded on the spot for that.
And the reports are somethings you submit to us PDFs, send us emails, sorry, submit them on model
and then we grade them over the course of the semester.
OK, that's all fair.
OK, let's let's move on.
Let's see what we'll learn in the in the in the labs.
This is a picture you've seen many times.
This is the transformation hierarchy.
And we will touch upon these three layers that I highlight here.
Most of the time we will understand how a processor works underneath the software layer and you will
touch on implementation details and you'll get hands on experience in digital circuit design and
implementation.
Now we will talk about how exactly you will get that experience later on in these slides.
In the end, you will hopefully have learned how to make trade-offs between performance and area or
the overall complexity in your digital designs or hardware implementations in later labs.
For example, we ask you to implement an optimization in your processor design that will come at a
cost but improve performance for certain workloads.
So that's exactly what will hopefully teach you how to make these trade-offs.
And you'll get hands on experience on hardware prototyping on field programmable gate.
AS that's Fpgas.
We will talk about these more.
You'll understand how to methodically debug your hardware implementations.
You'll use hardware description languages to describe your digital circuits basically, and you'll
use hardware design flow.
You'll learn about the hardware design flow using computer aided design tools that we will give you
access to in the labs.
So let's continue with a brief introduction to Fpgas.
These are Fpgas short for Field Programmable Gate Gate Array.
As I just mentioned, they look like this.
This is the rather old Spartan FPGA chip from Xilinx.
It isn't also called an integrated circuit or a chip.
These are embedded in a board with other components that they are there to enable various
applications and we will see such applications in the following slides.
So what makes them?
So what makes these FPGA so versatile, they can enable so many applications is basically they're
configurable, you can reconfigurable.
You configure the functions, the interconnections of these functions and the way they communicate
over input and output signals to realise almost any digital circuit you want to.
Now recall these slides from earlier lectures where we discussed where we basically sorted different
types of chips according to their purposes.
So if you go left to the to the left on the slide, you will have a more general purpose chip that
can execute any program and they're easy to use relatively, but they don't get you the best
performance and efficiency for a specialised use case.
And for that we want special purpose chips such as this Cerebras wafer scale engine here.
And they're relatively more difficult to program.
They are fit to a single use case typically, but they are very highly efficient.
Fpgas are somewhere in between those.
So these are relatively easy to program compared to those special purpose chips, but they're also be
able, they're also going to give you high performance energy efficiency for specialised use cases
that are not that CPS and GPS are not tailored for now we will look at where exactly FPGA are used
in today's systems.
And there I categorise these use cases under 4.
But there can be more, you can think of more of these use cases or categories perhaps they enable
acceleration of important workloads.
You can use them to test and characterise systems, and you can prototype new ideas using Fpgas, new
designs using Fpgas and you can deliver updatable hardware to the field using Fpgas.
These will become more clear as I give you the concrete examples and particularly testing and
characterisation will enable us to discover new phenomena, which I will touch upon next.
So let's look at how Fpgas enable acceleration of important workloads.
This is one example deep learning platform from Microsoft.
They developed this to enable real time machine learning inference in cloud computing systems and
they use these Fpgas to implement what they call a neural processing unit that access deep neural
network inference tasks and they're using it for computer vision and language processing.
This is another example from Amazon.
These are the F1 instances.
These are cloud hosted Fpgas that any user who don't perhaps have a business need for owning an FPGA
to use Fpgas to accelerate their own workloads.
They're highly customisable.
There's another example from the bioinformatics field, it's called Illumina Dragon.
This is an FPGA based platform to accelerate genomics analysis using using methods like mapping and
alignment, sorting and variant calling.
These are hopefully these things you're going to learn about in the upcoming lectures.
There are more FPGA based platforms that have been used to accelerate genomics analysis.
This is a work from our group in the past with the old Gatekeeper, the first FPGA based line on
filter to accelerate a key stage in DNA read mapping.
And after that we follow the up with Sneaky Snake to further accelerate the same stage of the read
mapping.
And both.
Both of these works were published in a very prominent bioinformatics conference.
And you can see many more insights into how FPGS can accelerate genome analysis in this paper.
I recommend you read it if you're interested.
And there are other use cases about.
There are other works that that develop the same, there will be FPGA for the same use case.
And here's more information on what you where you can find them.
There's a different use case.
This is accelerating climate modelling.
Climate modelling is also a very acceleratable per SE task using Fpgas.
And this paper was published in 2020.
You can find more about the genomics and the climate modelling acceleration works in this paper.
And this is the system that they used in these two prior works.
It provides significant performance and energy benefits over a conventional CPU based system, as you
can see here.
And this is another climate modelling acceleration work done using Fpgas.
So all that's to say, you can accelerate important workloads and provide significant energy and
performance benefits that otherwise would not be attainable with conventional systems.
FPGA has also enabled testing and characterization of systems.
This is one example from our group.
It's called.
It has two different names.
Soft MC is an early version of this infrastructure.
DMN is a newer version where we are able to test DM chips, real DM chips.
Using the low level DRM interface that over the years.
So I'm going to flash you some slides about information that you can see find about these
infrastructures.
But they have essentially over the years enabled us to make new discoveries, discover new phenomenon
about DRM operation.
So this is one of the setups that we have.
What you see here is an FPGA board.
Underneath this heat sink, there's an FPGA chip and there's a DRAM module here that we test using
this FPGA set up and we can control temperature.
As you can see here.
We have many different versions of this infrastructure to test different generations of DRAM chips.
And we have built a significantly large lab that has I think 80 of these chips now that allows us to
hopefully moving into future discovery even newer phenomena in DRAM.
Yeah, as I said, we have many of these and this enables us to discover new phenomena.
I'll talk about a few of these.
So raw hammer, maybe you've heard of it already in this course, even an older version of this
testing infrastructure enable the discovery of raw hammer.
And we have also done several other work following that similar work that uncovered more insights
into raw Hammer sensitivities and we uncovered the details of existing.
So raw hammer is a reliability problem.
And there's, there was some manufacturers claim to have fixed it in the past.
And in this paper we uncovered that those mitigations or those fixes were imperfect, then you could
easily bypass them and induce raw hammer errors.
So that becomes a security problem again.
So I'm going to flash here a bunch of papers that we've done following on this track of DRAM read
disturbance issues, RAW hammer and there's a bunch, there's quite a lot of them.
And these are all enabled by Fpgas basically.
And people, OK, you can use the DM Mendor like infrastructure to find out other phenomena like if
you enable this is not going to make too much sense to you right now.
But if you access different parts of the DMRA at the same time, which is not supported or which is
not a standard operation when you have Adm chip.
If you do that, you can generate random numbers, 2 random numbers inside your DM chips and you can
generate even more.
Or you can generate these numbers even faster.
If you open more than 4 rows in the previous paper, you open 4 rows, you can open more rows and you
can generate these relatively faster if you have the ability to open multiple rows at once.
You can implement boolean functions inside the DM chip.
You don't have to take the data out to your processor.
You can do these operations inside the DM chips in real DM chips.
And that's another thing that FPGA based infrastructures allowed us to uncover.
And this is another work that we did in the same direction.
So that's all about DM banner.
There's also a similar infrastructure you can easily, well, you can develop similar infrastructures
for other types of storage or memory technologies.
This is one for characterising flash memories.
And this led to the this work where we basically gain a deep understanding of problems and potential
solutions to those problems in flash chips.
Fpgas also enable prototyping of new ideas.
And in this one we prototype that that system that I mentioned where we were doing computation
inside the DM chip.
So this is a full system that's prototyped on the FPGA board.
So you have the processor core interacting at the DM chip and performing these operations inside the
DM chip.
And the whole thing is inside this board and you can program it however you want and used it and
demonstrate this functionality to the broader community.
And this is PIE DM.
That's, this is something else that builds on PIE DM and enables prototyping various DM techniques,
not just the ones you do inside the DM chip.
And there's also metasys that I want to highlight.
And this, in this one, we prototype a new architecture idea that allows the programmer to express
information beyond what's allowed by the standard instruction set architectures today.
So if you're going to learn about instruction set architectures in the following lectures, what that
interface gives you as a programmer is a bunch of instructions and some specification, but it
doesn't allow you to communicate all the potential information you as the programmer might know
about your own data and your program.
And this is 1 system that allows you to express that information to hardware we.
Prototype this in this board you can see and the paper we wrote, I got the best paper award from one
of the prominent conferences in Europe.
And this is more information about Metasys.
If you're interested, I'll also mention this one and this is in Barcelona Supercomputing Centre.
It's a very large scale FPGA infrastructure made-up of 96 of these boards.
They use them to basically emulate large scale chip designs.
So they say that this allows massive size register transfer level designs up to 700 million ASIC
application specific integrated circuit cells.
And I I will mention that this is one of the major use for Fpgas.
It's to prototype your hardware.
So many manufacturers specialised chips will cost you a lot.
So what people tend to do is they demonstrate that the the functionality and the benefits, potential
benefits of this specialised circuit using Fpgas first and then they can they they start
manufacturing their chips.
There are some other use cases.
Fpgas enable updatable hardware in the field and some examples to these are high bandwidth data
processing for experimental physics at CERN.
They have a huge FPGA footprint at CERN.
High frequency training is another use case, medical imaging and computation in space.
So this one I find very interesting.
NASA's Ingenuity helicopter, this is a picture of the helicopter on Mars surface and they have an
FPGA there that manages Ingenuity's operational state.
And if you think about it, computation in space, you need to be tolerant to errors because there,
there are high energy particles that keep hitting your chip.
And this reconfigurability in FPGA is actually allows you to deal with some of those problems in a
nice way.
If you can, you configure on the flight per SE, if you have a heart fault, if, if you have a failing
component in your FPGA, you can route around that.
You can reuse another component that you haven't used initially.
So these are the interesting use cases.
I hope that motivates you to learn about Fpgas beyond this course.
And those are what other people use, FPGA first.
So we're going to talk about what you will use them for this semester.
Now, do you have any questions so far?
OK, no.
Cool.
So this slide you've seen in a previous lecture, we're going to basically learn how microprocessors
work by programming Fpgas using these languages.
Here we're specifically going to use very long.
This is the FPGA board that you're going to have from the first lecture on.
This has a bunch of the FPGA chip is right here and it has a ton of different components here that I
highlight.
And you're going to basically see and touch most of them throughout the labs.
And I'll give you a high level summary of the labs at the end of the exercise.
You will have build a 32 bit microprocessor, whatever that means for you.
You'll learn about that later on running on that FPGA board and you'll program it and you'll do cool
things on it.
Hopefully it will be a small processor, but it's going to be able to execute any program.
And each week you will have a new exercise and not all exercises will require the FPGA board in the
first week.
You don't need the FPGA board.
You're encouraged to experiment with the board on your own.
And there's a little chance, very tiny chance we will have extra boards if you need them to use to
use them beyond the this course, but ask us basically, we might not have them this semester.
And you won't be able to destroy the board by just programming it.
So you can use a software tool chain relying on it that it won't break the board.
But you know, physically you can easily break the board, so don't break it.
So I'll go over the labs and this is the first one drawing a basic circuit.
We will do a comparison operation because comparison very important.
And you're going to do this on paper.
Basically you will have two digital signals.
And you will output 2 digits.
It's going to be a practice session sort of based on the last two lectures and no FPGA programming
involved.
I'm going to go over them relatively quickly because I think you'll be introduced to them throughout
other means as well.
And I don't have much time.
I want to talk about what's inside an FPGA.
I'll just give you a warning.
In Lab 4, typically the Lab 4 is a bit difficult because this is your introduction to sequential
circuits in the labs.
Don't get demotivated when you get to this lab.
We're going to be fine and our assistants are there to help you.
You'll implement an ALU, you'll test the ALU method methodically, and you will learn how digital
design testing is done.
And in Lab 7, you will write assembly code.
This is that instruction set architecture level language.
That I was talking about earlier and you will do some image manipulation tasks using assembly in lab
8.
This will be spread over 2 weeks.
You will design the processor that we talked about and you're going to run a snake program that will
appear as this thing that you see here in this animation on your 7 segment displays and, and on the
board.
And the last lab, you will add new instructions to your processor to improve performance.
OK.
So that's the summary for the labs.
I'll stop momentarily take questions if you have any.
Yes, good question.
Not everyone will get a robust box.
So there are the robust box.
Actually, we should maybe think about this.
But yeah, I mean, it's good if you can bring something anticipating that you won't get a robust box
to store the FPGA in to the lecture.
It's a small, it's a very small board.
So like a plastic food, a meal box would suffice.
It's it's would be good.
Yeah.
OK.
Yes, yeah, yeah.
So the question is, can, can we buy them individually?
Yes, we will provide you with links to the supplier after maybe we can share this announcement or
model.
Yeah, any other questions?
No questions.
Cool.
So recall that FPGA is a reconfigurable substrate and we also, I also want you to remember where it
basically lies on the general purpose to special purpose integrated circuit scale.
It's basically programmable, but can be used to implement specialised logic more efficiently than
CPUs and GPUs.
An FPGA is a mess of mesh of things or mess of things.
If I think both are OK, it's it's made-up of logic blocks, switch blocks, interconnects and IO
blocks.
And to map your digital design onto the FPGA, you basically configure each such thing in the FPGA.
So this is a more detailed picture of what's inside an FPGA.
We have look up tables inside what we call configurable logic blocks or CL BS.
You will see that short name often there's switch boxes and there are connection boxes like this one
here.
And interestingly, if you look at the hardware footprint, most of the hardware in the FPGA is
interconnect.
So only a small fraction of area is occupied by look up tables and your configuration memory that's
used to basically drop things around.
And we rely on this interconnect to realise complex functions.
So this is what connects look up tables are configurable logic blocks to each other.
There's a different view of the previous picture.
So this I'm I'm going to show you to better explain how routing can be done on on an FPGA.
And this is 1 model and FPGA doesn't have to look like this, but this is a relatively reliable
model.
This is an switch box or an S box.
It connects horizontal and vertical wires on the FPGA mesh.
In this example the connections are hard wired as you can see, so they are not programmable.
But you can also imagine a programmable switch box substrate right?
In more advanced Fpgas this is a connection box.
It connects neighboring look up tables to each other and also the outputs to vertical lines.
And the connection box is made-up of two things, basically and multiplexer, which you already know
about at this point.
And to connect this O signal, this O signal to this Y signal, you can use what's called a pass
transistor.
It looks like this.
So it's gated by a signal originating from your configuration memory that you use to connect
different parts of the FPGA to each other.
And basically that's how you connect.
That's one way to connect vertical wires to horizontal wires coming out of your look up tables or
configurable logic blocks.
Does anyone have any idea what else you could have used here?
Hint is basically in the.
You've seen it in the yesterday's lecture.
It's another component you could use instead of the pass transistor.
Yes, I was going to say a tri-state buffer, but CMOS is yeah, it's, it's the more specifically a
tri-state buffer you could.
Used here to gate the transmission between the O signal and Y signal.
So you would still gate it with the signal from configuration memory, but it will come at a higher
cost, larger area cost, it will develop a more reliable signal.
But everything is a trade off.
So this I think gets us to a point where we have solved all the mysteries of an FPGA and
fundamentally all Fpgas have these building blocks.
They have more added on top and we'll talk about them if time permits.
But this is the fundamentals.
You also have seen multiplexes in previous lecture, how you can use them to make look up tables.
So I'm going to talk about it in a bit more detail.
So how do you program a look up table to implement a function?
You have a multiplexer and a bunch of data values that this multiplexer selects from the input
signal to This multiplexer chooses one of the signals as you've seen earlier.
And I will just argue that a three look up table, 3 input look up table can implement any 3 bit
function.
And you can try to prove this on your own time.
And we're going to walk through this example of a function that outputs a logic one when there are
at least two logic ones in a three bit input using a look up table.
So this is AC implementation.
If you were to implement this function in C, you would do something like this, but you can also use
switch case statements.
And this more naturally represents what you would have in the look up table.
So the way you would fill out this look up table then is when the input is all zero, there are less
than two ones in that input bits.
So you would fill this up with 0 and you will fill up every single input combination, the and data
values corresponding to input combinations based on the switch case statement here.
Basically your mocks will only output one if the input bits are set in a way that should satisfy the
function.
So this implements this look up table, implements this function.
And how do you implement more complex functions than this?
Basically you connect multiple look up tables to each other and in FPGA chip you will have multiple
like many thousands of 10s of thousands of these look up tables and configurable logic blocks.
And I'll show you one example.
This is about DRAM vendors.
So DRAM vendors hardware logic implemented in an FPGA.
What you see here is a device view.
So these blue blocks are used by DRAM vendors design in the FPGA.
These are each one of these are either configurable logic blocks or other specialised blocks in an
FPGA and we highlight DM managed register file in red and this is what you see when you zoom into a
single logic slice.
This is very interesting because it's made-up of things you've seen so far in the lectures and
nothing else.
This is AD flip flop.
It's a specialised 8 bit carry unit for when you want to more basically fat when you want to convey
the carry of an AD operation faster.
A 2 by 1 Max and a 64 entry look up table or a six input look up table.
So in the logic design tool we will use in the labs, you can even peek into the configuration
details of each look up table that you have implemented in your hardware and the truth table that
this look up table realises.
And I'm putting these all to say that modern FPGA tools are extremely powerful and you'll get to use
them in the labs.
And by now we've gotten some good insight into what an FPGA is and how it works underneath.
And besides these fundamental properties that we've seen modern Fpgas have more things for thousands
or 10s of thousands of look up tables.
There's distributed on chip memory, specialised on chip memory.
There are hard coded special purpose blocks for high performance operations like a memory interface,
low latency and high bandwidth chip IO, off chip IO, and sometimes even general purpose processors
inside an FPGA.
So that's what such an FPGA looks like.
These are all different components inside this single chip and only a small fraction of that is
programmable logic or the FPGA itself.
This is another more recent example.
There's programmable logic, there's a lot of memory related stuff and a lot of off chip high
performance interface.
So FP GS look like they can.
They have everything we need for almost any application.
I'm going to wrap up by going over advantages and disadvantages of FPGA.
So the first advantage is you can implement your algorithm directly in hardware that gets you high
specialisation and potential performance and energy.
It has lower development costs versus an ASIC in a specialised chip.
It has short time to market and you.
Can reconfigure it in the field.
Now the disadvantage is it's not as fast or power efficient as it would be if you were to basically
manufacture a chip based on your digital circuit.
And the reconfigurable comes at the cost.
It has significant area and latency overhead to this otherwise specialised chip that you would
build.
OK, so how are you going to program them in the labs?
For the most part, you're not going to program Fpgas.
You'll basically ask the tool to program the FPGA.
What you're going to do is you'll take this problem definition that we described in the lab
handouts.
You're going to use Verilog to describe a solution for that task.
This is your task.
And the rest will be done by the we've other tools that we will use and you will take the output of
the tool and put it in the FPGA.
That's your design in the FPGA.
In real life, this is what the tool looks like.
Vivado, it provides tools to simulate your designs.
Besides implementing them in FPGA.
You can use it for debugging and this will be installed in all computer rooms.
So you don't need to install this on your own laptops and we don't recommend you try to install
them.
You're welcome to try and install them, but we don't recommend it.
Vivado is not open source, but it's freely downloadable.
Yeah, there's a demo here that you can on your own time go over.
It's you can watch this demo that shows you how to program a keyboard application on a real basis,
three FPGA board that you will have.
So I recommend you go over this, but it's not it's not required, but it will help you a lot in the
second lab.
I want you to keep in mind that you don't need to install Vivato on your laptop, but we have some.
We can provide some help, but we don't officially support this.
That piece is already have it installed.
I kindly ask you not to ask T as to grade you outside lab hours.
Please ask them to grade you during the lab hours.
And please be careful to submit your lab files in the correct format.
We will announce what the correct format means.
Double check your uploaded files and we I'll let you know now that incorrectly uploaded submissions
will receive 0 points.
So double check and double check your grades also and let us know if something's missing as early as
possible.
That's all for this lecture.
Thank you for your attention.